[SPEAKER_00]: Bhante, is there a way to speed up my practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the problem is that question assumes you already know what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're going to try to speed something up that you kind of already know what it's about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, the more important question is, do I know what the practice is, so that I can speed it up?
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, you can read the suttas, you can even, like, rationalize about what the obstacles of your practice are, but an obstacle is defined as an obstacle by knowing what the goal is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you don't know what the goal is, how can you know what the obstacles are, so that you can then remove them and then speed up the practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, for as long as you don't have the right view yet, you shouldn't assume like, okay, I'm already doing the practice, semi-correctly, but it's just not going fast enough, which is what most people assume, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sort of already mostly going in the right direction, but it's just, it just takes time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I just need to kind of dedicate more effort to it or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, more than nine times out of ten, again, well, if you don't have the right view, if you're not a sotāpanna, your idea of the practice is the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your idea of the practice is the obstacle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Start trying to figure out what the practice is, abandoning wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how do you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by admitting, first of all, that your views are not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't, then you, again, you might even read the suttas, you might hear stuff from the Buddha's own mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as he himself said, when somebody comes with the the notion that they understand what they don't understand, that is a categorical obstacle for them to enter the path
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, when they hear even the right thing, they sort of absorb it and sort of mold it into the thing that they already created for themselves, which, again, is most likely wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you can hear... you see it all the time, like how people would parrot the suttas,
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, even before judging who is right and who is wrong, you see two people holding completely different views and quoting the same sutta to support their points, which shows you that, like, yeah, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: If it were all about just that information that you can just transmit from one person to the other, and then your view is right, just based on how you express it, then that wouldn't happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you'd have everybody agreeing on the same things, even though... just because the information is the same, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in that case, you can see how the information lands differently, based on the assumptions that you have behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, recognize... because, you know, the criteria for knowing that you don't know what the practice is, is that you're still subject to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that you kind of externally haven't matched some kind of idea or sort of threshold.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that very immediate recognition of, in day-to-day life, when problems arise, I feel trapped and I still need to do something, I still need to hope, I still need to sort of move variables around and expect that hopefully I won't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, unless that's not the case anymore, and you're free from doubt, as to how you can be free from suffering in every situation, regardless of what it is, then you can't be trying to speed up your practice, because you still don't know what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you knew what the practice was, you'd be free from doubt, that again, in any situation, you know the way out, and you wouldn't be trapped anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, all those teachings that the Buddha gave to, you know, like, the sense of urgency and don't be negligent, you know, it was all based on the right view as the foundation.
[SPEAKER_01]: To monks who had already been... they were clear about what they had to do, they were just not doing it as diligently as they should.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, to ask the question in a different way, are there any factors that support the questioning of one's views, that accelerate?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, see, everybody has kind of like situations where they know that they suffer,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or they know that they're still subject to craving, to defilements, but they kind of explain it away, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like not being relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like something that sort of... it will sort itself out, or it's not a big deal, or it's just how it is, it's just my personality or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start uncovering those things and you start realizing just basically the extent of your non-development, that gives you the sense of like, okay, so it can't possibly be right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever I think the practice is, however right it feels, you see, anything shorter than that sort of direct measurement,
[SPEAKER_01]: Could still be wrong, because you could, you know, even rely on an external reference point, which is what this, what's it called, Kalama Sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this ascetic is my teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: He agrees that I do understand the teaching that he teaches.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, what if he's wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if he doesn't... What if he does understand it, but he doesn't see how you don't understand it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he will tell you, yes, you do understand the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, anything except this direct comparison of your own ability to overcome suffering,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still going to be able to mislead you, and not show you just how much work you still need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically all of what you see in modern traditions and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like all these goalposts that are externally defined, as in like, okay, you get this experience, and then you get the next experience, and then when you enter this samādhi that has this characteristic, it means you're at this and this stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precisely, that's why you can have so many people who complete all those stages, backwards and forwards, and then you find out that they, whatever, have been breaking basic precepts for years.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, see, if they hadn't dismissed those tendencies that they would have seen in themselves if they were honest, like how their mind was still pressuring them towards this or that thing, and they had dug deeper into those things, they would have realized, like, yes, I can't possibly claim that I know the way out of craving, because look at what's happening to my own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you don't see it as important,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can pretty much make it, like, completely disappear from your point of view, if you exercise that cover up long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in fact, the Buddha said it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The basis for faith, which you could pretty much say, is basically that sense of urgency, that sense of, like, there is this this resolve that you get when you realize there is something I need to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: The basis for that is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like an external inspiration.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing how you personally are still suffering in ways that, you know, again, would be obvious if you just look for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that it's like concealed or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you're used to just covering it up and making it seem unimportant when actually the arrow of suffering is very much touching you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, things like precepts, non-distraction,
[SPEAKER_00]: Spending time in seclusion, those could be all things that you can do without the right view, that would help you to reduce the cover-ups that you would usually do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but let's say for most people, for the average lay person.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if those things were actually nothing themselves, then you wouldn't have so many cases of monks who have been practicing for decades and clearly still have wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, it's like you can get used to that environment, to those circumstances, very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, genuinely, you wouldn't want to disrobe, let's say.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you could, for example, cover up your own dependence on your tradition, as something that, like, if you were placed in a completely different environment, where people didn't agree with the values that you have,
[SPEAKER_01]: And there wasn't that kind of external reinforcement to tell you that what you're doing is right, you would fall apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just one example.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that, you know, it's... Because, again, it varies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depends on the person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for somebody, they may not care about breaking the precepts and not care about tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: For another person, they don't care about breaking the precepts, they do care about tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other person do cares about the precepts but not about tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the thing that for you personally, if you reflect honestly, like this sort of hits me at the core?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's probably not going to be just one thing, but it's kind of like you start uncovering, basically, all these... You'll find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start finding it left and right, eventually, but it's just like... Again, you were so used to just explaining it away, even sometimes with things in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, imagine somebody who reads the suttas and says, oh, an arahant still experiences pleasant and unpleasant feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they justify all sorts of, like, again, even breaking precepts and stuff, that, like, oh, no, it's because an arahant still has these, these kind of, he still experienced feelings, so, you know, all this is justified.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it can go extremely far in how you can, again, cover these things up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would see it at, like, all these supposed arahants that exist and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means, like, they completely don't accept at all, acknowledge at all, all the defilements that they still have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't feel like a defilement when you act out of it, when all the... when you're used to acting out of it, when all the circumstances around it allow you to act out of it, and you can just sort of like get over it quickly, whenever it comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it boils down to self-honesty?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, even the Buddha, like, he wouldn't have become the Buddha had he not realized, wait, yes, I had developed all this lofty stuff, but can I still suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he realized, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And most people would read that and sort of think like, oh, yeah, of course, but... like, again, most of the time, with way less development than that, you're already covering things up and not acknowledging how you're actually still suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, actually, again...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's another thing that's overlooked.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first noble truth is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, we already have that understood, like we're already suffering, we know what that is, and then now it's just about discovering the cessation and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you don't even recognize your own suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're used to covering it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, how can you be practicing and speeding up the practice of overcoming something that you don't clearly see?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would then be the difference between unpleasant feeling and actual suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's what I said before, like, does it hit you to the core?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, do you feel immediately that you already need to do something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there an action that if you weren't able to do it, you would just be boiling in this discomfort?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the arrow that the Buddha talks about, that it kind of hits you to the heart.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can see, throughout your day, that you experience unpleasant things, everybody necessarily experiences unpleasant things, that don't actually hit them in that way, that don't actually cause them to enter the state of compulsion of having to do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just an unpleasant feeling and you... you don't have much of an issue withstanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, there are other things that, like, if you were to... again, if you were to reflect honestly, you would see, like, as soon as this arises, you would see your mind immediately already leaning towards some sort of response.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it goes hand in hand with action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Khamma, as the Buddha called it, like the impulse towards action, is another way of describing what you abandon when you develop your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that immediate sort of like... whether you do it or not, it's just an impulse there to respond to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, precepts and stuff, like, for most people, that's... that's... that's gonna already reveal it, but you can have plenty of situations where your impulse to respond isn't on the level of breaking the precepts, for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to say something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if it's like a... again, it's not a... like impolite, harsh speech and sort of this clear violation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might even be the most polite thing and might seem good to everybody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if you succeed in doing it,
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you had to do it, that's already suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even if you are able to do it every single time the impulse comes up, merely having the impulse and being pressured into it, it's already suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, just imagine, even if somebody forces you to do something and you're perfectly able to go ahead with that demand, and nobody punishes you or anything, but the fact that you were forced, that's in itself suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, suffering, in that sense, would then be the inability to stay or to not act out of unpleasant feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but you have to keep in mind that you basically, like, you catch yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already...
[SPEAKER_00]: You catch yourself already within suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like you're going to see the unpleasant feeling, and then you're going to see, oh, I have the impulse to act, and then, like, you know, you're going to realize that you already are caught up in the impulse to to get rid of some unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, if you were aware of the impulse, and it were a matter of like, okay, I'm gonna follow it or not, that wouldn't be... that wouldn't really be an impulse.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point of the mind, and that's why it's compared to an animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like it's doing stuff even without you telling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can sort of afterwards try to contain it and stuff, but like, it has its own impulses that come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one finds oneself pressured by an unpleasant feeling, one recognizes this impulse, wanting to get rid of that unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes it happens as well that despite recognizing the impulse, one still acts out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that the case?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but you wouldn't be able to act out of it if you recognized it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what you have to... see, ties into the whole thing I was describing before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even your notion of what recognizing the impulse means might not be correct, because otherwise you wouldn't have acted out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in fact, that's why in the suttas, the Buddha describes the satipaṭṭhāna of the mind, not as like when a bhikkhu has a lustful mind, he changes the lustful mind for a different mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says he maintains perspective over the lustful mind, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And based on this practice, he abides independent, not taking up anything in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, if you actually recognize an impulse, as it is the impulse of the citta, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not only will you be incapable of acting out of it, that mere recognition is already training the mind, and making that impulse subside, because it's like trapped.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if it's still there, there is no expression of it, so it has to run out of fuel.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that's actually like, see, when you... let's say, any desire comes up in your mind, and then you have this phase where, like, you can sort of battling with yourself about it, doubting, should I do it, should I not do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, as soon as you go with it, the question disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, well, of course, you can... it can come back and stuff, but it will never be there, and it will never be magnified to the same extent as if you were to stop again and reconsider, like, should I do this, should I not do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fact that you're in it already means you can't consider it with the same amount of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why having that right level of perspective prevents you from getting into it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting into it even with your welcoming, let alone actions of body and speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, of course, like, if you catch yourself acting out of something, it doesn't mean like, okay, so, because I can't see the impulse, whatever, I'll just keep...
[SPEAKER_00]: Acting out verbally and physically...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, yeah, verbally and physically and then later I'll do something else to discern the impulse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, you have to stop doing the things that prevent you from recognizing the impulse as it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the precepts are for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, it's not showing you the impulse or clarifying the perspective of what the impulse actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just stopping you from doing the things that definitely cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, well, the rest is for you to clarify that view, to, again, recognize your own experience of suffering as it arises, recognizing what is the unpleasant feeling and what is that kind of compulsion to respond to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is only going to happen if you want to recognize that difference, if you are trying to make the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because anybody could just keep the precepts for any random reason, and they're not making that effort, they're not going to discern that difference, and they're not going to understand suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But would you then say that it's a matter of not recognizing it as an impulse at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or not being able to maintain the perspective of it's an impulse?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as you said, you drop it at one point, because you can't just withstand the... Yeah, well, see, you can recognize it as an impulse.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you might even constantly recognize it as an impulse.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is a difference in the quality or type of that recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, you see even in these, like, meditation techniques, how they would describe that people would, quote-unquote, see their mental states arising and ceasing and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if it, let's say, it actually was, because there has to be some link, it's not like you're talking about greed arose and there was genuinely nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is, you're seeing it with that kind of overly focused direct attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means,
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if that is an impulse, the root impulse, which is the one that matters, it remains completely unseen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as, why am I observing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I trying to get something out of this?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, even the restlessness to figure out what the suffering is,
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the actual impulse, in that scenario.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the root of the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, somebody could be thinking, okay, let me figure out what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me look closer at these things that are happening in my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, they see the greed coming up, and they see the aversion coming up, and the restlessness coming up, but they don't see how that whole endeavor is underlain by a mind of restlessness that's pressuring me to do this observation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that it's inherently so, but at that time, that was the pressure that was driving your experience, and you didn't see it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the need for yoniso manasikāra, that's described, and that's why it's a condition for the right view as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because anybody can talk about greed and stuff, but, you see, it's not just the random things that you can point to in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's what is the root of it right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the thing that it converges on?
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing where you're actually, let's say, most emotionally engaged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can have a thought of greed that just comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, precisely, you're seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're seeing it come up like you're not engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not an issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what you are engaged with is that restlessness of let me observe this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, precisely, the stuff that you don't see is the stuff that hinders you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The stuff that captivates your perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's so important to always be reclarifying, like, that intention behind your actions, even on the mental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why am I watching my mind right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you would see, oh, my mind is actually in a state of restlessness that's associated with an action of watching my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize, in order to see my mind, I would have to stop watching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I would be seeing it on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you then speed up the practice when you have the right view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, it wouldn't be a different principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, if you had the right view, it just means you have the criteria to recognize what's an obstruction now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be exactly the same thing as in, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be uncovering the things that you are excusing yourself in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the little forms of greed, aversion and delusion that you're excusing yourself in regard to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only difference is now, like, you wouldn't have to doubt your criteria for what is greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because having that criteria is what the right view is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your practice would be obstructed for exactly the same reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're acting out of stuff, not including it, making up whatever excuses you could come up with, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, the mind is receiving the feel that it needs for these states to continue, for these pressures to continue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would never be like, oh, you you kind of commit to some special kind of practice, like go in a special retreat and stuff, that will speed things up and bring them closer to the surface.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is like, if you did that, it would be as a as a way of you not acting out of your mental states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when people look for these sort of ways to speed up the practice, the view that floats behind that is like, there are these things that you can do, which are wholesome in themselves, regardless of why I'm doing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And somebody who has the right view would not be able to think that, because they would have understood it's exactly the intention that determines the quality of the action, regardless of what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, they wouldn't be able to commit to like, oh, I'll spend three months even doing exactly to the letter everything that the Buddha said, because they would know that even that they can do wrong, with racistness, with greed, with all these mental states.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they would instead put first
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the state of a mind, seeing whether I'm acting out of it, if it's unwholesome, and then everything else is secondary to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like, that's why the practice would be kind of hindered by you, or slowed down by you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you couldn't have the perfect circumstances that would have allowed you to commit to this method hard enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you could have circumstances that are making it more likely for you to make wrong choices, as in prioritize dealing with external things compared to restraining your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you're, let's say, in an overly busy environment, and then, like, because of your own lack of training, then you, you sort of... makes it easier for you to distract yourself with things that are going on externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, it's because of the choices that you're making.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even when the suttas speak about the things that hinder the progression of somebody with the right view, of someone in training,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's their delight in work, their delight in sleep, their delight in company.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, because they happen to be in such and such environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because they are delighting in these things, they're pursuing them, that hinders their progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it automatically means they're putting first something, whatever it is, external, over that crucial question of why am I doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they would see that they're doing it out of delight and that it cannot possibly be wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if people take up those things as an external practice, like, okay, the less I sleep, the better.
[SPEAKER_00]: The less I'm with people, the better.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more I'm in seclusion, the better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but do you understand what the light is?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically, like, many people would start out with this assumption, like, pretty much, it automatically carries the light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I don't need to question it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just automatically carries the light.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if, let's say, you factually stop delighting in sleep as a result of that practice, and you overcame the need for sleep, you are not any closer to actually developing the right view, which means you will lose that eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, not just that, but you are acting out of other stuff that you don't see, even if you overcame this one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, yeah, you can do whatever practices to... and then, factually, you could hear stories of people who... their lust diminished or whatever, their anger diminished or whatever, but what's the full picture there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what about everything else?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they more sensitive to...
[SPEAKER_01]: People disagreeing with them, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are they more sensitive to having an environment that they don't like?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you would see, inevitably, one of those things will have to be there if they don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you don't see craving, you have to be acting out of it in some form.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be pure accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: How would one then remove the delight out of those very things that you mentioned?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, first you have to understand what delight is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... You could take the same thread that I described before.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even like that the action is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because some things are going to be pleasant and you can't possibly prevent that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even if you go out of your way,
[SPEAKER_01]: To prevent it, it's not possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when something is pleasant, is there an impulse to seek more of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Regardless of what it is,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, of course, you could say, you know, yeah, I don't care about food, I don't care about sexuality, I don't care about entertainment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is there something for you that is pleasant, that when it arises, you have this basically, like, if I don't go for more of it, my mind is kind of eating itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's what you would need to guard yourself against.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's not there now, that doesn't mean you just... because even the suttas say, that same one I described, it says, when your mind is not affected with greed, not affected with aversion, not affected with delusion, you still have to know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still have to keep perspective in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, it's like, oh, I'll just leave the bank, because there are no thieves here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't need to guard the door anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, you will start to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it's always like you catch yourself having already fallen into the light.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like you sort of see the thing coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that were possible, you would never fall into it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like you catch yourself already delighting in something, you catch your mind already having this momentum, and then you realize... well, first of all, you... if you have that perspective developed, you see that the light arisen, that's the practice of somebody with the right view, and then that automatically kind of corrects the picture, and by absolute extension, they won't be able to keep acting out externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, initially, like, okay, let's say it's it's not 100% clear what the light is, but you can see these actions that, like, even with reasoning, you could say that's almost 90% chance not wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, okay, well, you stop it and you try to... keeping in mind still, like, I still need to understand what the light is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't feel justified and like, okay, now I just... every time this direction comes up for me, I just deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, that's still carrying an assumption that, that... Basically, it's not doing justice to how much you still don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, like, sometimes you could deny something that wasn't actually unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not safer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it keeps reinforcing the wrong criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Denying something that's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it keeps, keeps kind of feeding that wrong emphasis that you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there isn't really a method, in that sense, when you don't see these things for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, if you keep in mind that you don't see it for yourself, and you keep the motivation and the sense of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Of perspective of why it matters that you don't see it for yourself, because, you know, random drunkard in in the middle of a village could say, I don't care, I don't understand the Buddha's teaching, because he doesn't understand why that's relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to be careful that it doesn't become like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, I recognize, I still don't have the right view and stuff, but it's it's kind of like this this externally projected ideal that because I'm a Buddhist, I should have the right view and this is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... you see that all the time in people, like they would recognize that they have the right view, but it would almost be like completely fine with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you don't recognize the level of problems that this creates for you.